The world is filled with incredible objects
يزخر عالمنا بأشياء لا تصدّق
and rich cultural heritage.
وتراث ثقافي ثري.
And when we get access to them,
وعندما تسنح الفرصة لنا للولوج إليها،
we are blown away, we fall in love.
تسحرنا،ونقع في حبّها.
But most of the time,
ولكن في معظم الأحيان،
the world's population is living without real access to arts and culture.
لا تسنح الفرصة لسكان العالم من الوصول إلى الفنون والثقافة.
What might the connections be when we start exploring our heritage,
ماهي أساليب الاتصال الممكنة إذا رغبنا باستكشاف تراثنا،
the beautiful locations and the art in this world?
هل هي المواقع الجميلة والفنون في هذا العالم؟
Before we get started in this presentation,
قبل البدأ بهذا العرض
I just want to take care of a few housekeeping points.
أودّ لفت نظركم إلى بعض النقاط العامة.
First, I am no expert in art or culture.
أولًا، أنا لست خبيرًا بالفن والثقافة.
I fell into this by mistake, but I'm loving it.
الصدفة هي من جمعتني بهم ولكني أعشقهم.
Secondly, all of what I'm going to show you
ثانيًا، كل ما سأعرضه عليكم
belongs to the amazing museums, archives and foundations
ينتمي إلى المتاحف الرائعة، والمحفوظات والمؤسسات
that we partner with.
من تربطنا بهم علاقة الشراكة.
None of this belongs to Google.
لا ينتمي أي منها إلي غوغل.
And finally, what you see behind me
وأخيرًا، ما تشاهدونه خلفي
is available right now on your mobile phones,
متاح الآن عبر هواتفكم المحمولة،
on your laptops.
وعلى حواسبكم المحمولة.
This is our current platform, where you can explore
هذه هي منصّتنا، حيث يمكنكم استكشاف
thousands of museums and objects at your fingertips,
آلاف المتاحف والمجسّمات في متناول يدكم،
in extremely high-definition detail.
بتفاصيل غاية في الدقة.
The diversity of the content is what's amazing.
تكمن الروعة في تنوع المحتوى.
If we just had European paintings,
لو كان لدينا فقط لوحات أوروبية،
if we just had modern art,
أو فن معاصر فقط،
I think it gets a bit boring.
فأعتقد أن هذا سيصبح مملاً.
For example, this month, we launched the "Black History" channel
على سبيل المثال، أطلقنا هذا الشهر قناة "التاريخ الأسود"
with 82 curated exhibitions,
التي بها 82 معرضًا مختلفًا،
which talk about arts and culture in that community.
تتحدث عن الفنون والثقافة في ذلك المجتمع.
We also have some amazing objects from Japan,
لدينا أيضًا أشياء مدهشة من اليابان،
centered around craftsmanship, called "Made in Japan."
تتمحور حول الحرفية وتدعى "صنع في اليابان".
And one of my favorite exhibitions,
وأحد أكثر المعارض التي أفضلها،
which actually is the idea of my talk,
والذي في الحقيقة يمثل فكرة حديثي اليوم،
is -- I didn't expect to become a fan of Japanese dolls.
هو-- أنني لم أعتقد يومًا أن أصبح مولعًا بالدمى اليابانية.
But I am, thanks to this exhibition,
ولكني كذلك، والشكر يعود لهذا المعرض،
that has really taught me about the craftsmanship
والذي بالفعل علمني الحرفيّة
behind the soul of a Japanese doll.
التي تكمن وراء روح الدمية اليابانية.
Trust me, it's very exciting.
ثقوا بي، إنها مثيرة للإهتمام.
Take my word for it.
ثقوا بكلامي.
So, moving on swiftly.
إذا، لننتقل بسرعة إلى الموضوع.
One quick thing I wanted to showcase in this platform,
الأمر الذي أردت تسليط الضوء عليه سريعا في هذه المنصّة،
which you can share with your kids and your friends right now,
والذي يمكنكم الآن أن تشاركوه مع أولادكم وأصدقائكم،
is you can travel to all these amazing institutions virtually, as well.
أنه يمكنكم السفر افتراضيًا إلى هذه الصروح،
One of our recent ideas was with The Guggenheim Museum in New York,
إحدى أفكارنا الحديثة كانت تتعلق بمتحف غوغنهايم في نيويورك،
where you can get a taste of what it might feel like
حيث تختبرون الإحساس والشعور
to actually be there.
الحقيقي كأنكم هناك.
You can go to the ground floor
يمكنكم الذهاب إلى الطابق الأرضيّ
and obviously, most of you, I assume, have been there.
ومن الواضح، أن معظمكم، على ما أعتقد، سبق أن زاره.
And you can see the architectural masterpiece that it is.
حيث يمكنكم مشاهدة تلك التحفة المعمارية.
But imagine this accessibility for a kid in Bombay
ولكن تخيلوا أن يشعر بهذا الإحساس طفل من بومباي
who's studying architecture,
يدرس فن العمارة،
who hasn't had a chance to go to The Guggenheim as yet.
لم تسنح له الفرصة بأن يزور متحف غوغنهايم بعد.
You can obviously look at objects in the Guggenheim Museum,
يمكنكم أن تشاهدوا المجسمات بوضوح في متحف غوغنهايم،
you can obviously get into them and so on and so forth.
يمكنكم الوصول إليهم بوضوح وهكذا دواليك.
There's a lot of information here.
يوجد الكثير من المعلومات هنا.
But this is not the purpose of my talk today.
ولكن هذا ليس مقصد حديثي اليوم.
This exists right now.
هذا موجود الآن.
What we now have are the building blocks to a very exciting future,
ما لدينا الآن هي اللبنات الأساسية لمستقبل مثير جداً،
when it comes to arts and culture
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالفنون والثقافة
and accessibility to arts and culture.
وإمكانية الولوج إليهم.
So I am joined today onstage by my good friend and artist in residence
ينضم إليّ اليوم على هذه المنصّة صديقي العزيز والفنان
at our office in Paris, Cyril Diagne,
من مكتبنا في باريس، سيريل دياني،
who is the professor of interactive design
وهو أستاذ التصميم التفاعلي
at ECAL University in Lausanne, Switzerland.
في جامعة (إيكال) في لوزان، سويسرا.
What Cyril and our team of engineers have been doing
ما قام به سيريل وفريقنا من المهندسين
is trying to find these connections and visualize a few of these.
هو محاولة إيجاد هذه الصلات وتصوّر البعض من هذه.
So I'm going to go quite quick now.
إذاً سأسرع قليلاً الآن.
This object you see behind me -- oh, just clarification:
هذا الجسم الذي تشاهدونه خلفي -- لا هذا توضيح:
Always, seeing the real thing is better.
دائماً، رؤية الشيء الحقيقي أفضل.
In case people think I'm trying to replicate the real thing.
في حال اعتقد البعض أنّي أحاول تقليد الأشياء الحقيقية.
So, moving on.
إذاً، لنتابع.
This object you see behind me is the Venus of Berekhat Ram.
هذا الجسم الذي تشاهدونه خلفي هو فينوس بيراخات رام.
It's one of the oldest objects in the world,
وهو أحد أقدم المجسمات في العالم،
found in the Golan Heights around 233,000 years ago,
عثر عليه في مرتفعات الجولان قبل حوالي 233,000 عام،
and currently residing at the Israel Museum in Jerusalem.
موجود حالياً في متحف إسرائيل في القدس.
It is also one of the oldest objects on our platform.
وهو أحد أقدم المجسمات على منصتنا.
So let's zoom.
إذاً دعونا نكبّر الصورة.
We start from this one object.
نبدأ من هذا الجسم تحديداً.
What if we zoomed out
ماذا لو قمنا بتصغير الصورة
and actually tried to experience our own cultural big bang?
وحاولنا فعلياً اختبار انفجارنا الثقافي العظيم؟
What might that look like?
ما الذي سيبدو عليه الأمر؟
This is what we deal with on a daily basis at the Cultural Institute --
هذا ما نعمل عليه يومياً في المعهد الثقافي --
over six million cultural artifacts curated and given to us by institutions,
تم إنشاء أكثر من ستة ملايين قطعة أثرية ثقافية وأعطيت لنا من قبل المؤسسات،
to actually make these connections.
حتى وصلنا فعلياً إلى هذه الصلات.
You can travel through time,
يمكنكم السفر عبر الزمن،
you can understand more about our society through these.
ومن خلالها يمكنكم فهم مجتمعنا أكثر.
You can look at it from the perspective of our planet,
يمكنكم النظر إليها من منظور كوكبنا،
and try to see how it might look without borders,
لمحاولة معرفة ما الذي يبدو عليه دون حدود،
if we just organized art and culture.
إذا نظمنا الفنون والثقافة.
We can also then plot it by time,
ثم يمكننا حبكها مع الوقت،
which obviously, for the data geek in me, is very fascinating.
وهذا بالطبع، لشخص مهووس بالبيانات مثلي، أمر في غاية الروعة.
You can spend hours looking at every decade
يمكنكم قضاء ساعات من البحث في كل عقد من الزمن
and the contributions in that decade and in those years
وفي كل المساهمات خلال ذلك العقد وتلك السنوات
for art, history and cultures.
في الفنون، والتاريخ والثقافات.
We would love to spend hours showing you each and every decade,
نرغب في قضاء ساعات لنريكم كل عقد من العقود،
but we don't have the time right now.
ولكن لا يسعنا الوقت الآن.
So you can go on your phone and actually do it yourself.
لذلك يمكنكم استخدام جهازكم ورؤيتها بأنفسكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But if you don't mind and can hold your applause till later,
وإذا كنتم لا تمانعون وتؤجلون تصفيقكم لوقت لاحق،
I don't want to run out of time,
لا أريد أن يدركني الوقت،
because I want to show you a lot of cool stuff.
لأني أريدكم أن تشاهدوا أشياء رائعة.
So, just very quickly:
إذاً، وبسرعة:
you can move on from here to another very interesting idea.
يمنكم التنقل من فكرة مثيرة للاهتمام إلى أخرى.
Beyond the pretty picture,
ما وراء الصورة الجميلة،
beyond the nice visualization,
ما وراء التصوير الجميل،
what is the purpose, how is this useful?
ما هو الهدف، وكيف يكون كلّ هذا مفيداً؟
This next idea comes from discussions with curators
جاءت الفكرة التالية من نقاشنا مع أمناء المتاحف
that we've been having at museums,
خلال وجودنا هناك،
who, by the way, I've fallen in love with,
والذين، بالمناسبة، أغرمت بهم،
because they dedicate their whole life to try to tell these stories.
لأنهم كرّسوا حياتهم في محاولة رواية هذه القصص.
One of the curators told me, "Amit, what would it be like
أحد أمناء المتاحف قال لي "أميت،كيف سيبدو الأمر"
if you could create a virtual curator's table
"لو أنك صنعت جدولاً افتراضيًا للأمناء"
where all these six million objects
"حيث تكون كل الستة ملايين مجسّم"
are displayed in a way for us to look at the connections between them?"
"معروضة بشكل يسمح لنا بالنظر إلى الصلات فيما بينها؟"
You can spend a lot of time, trust me, looking at different objects
ثقوا بكلامي، يمكنكم قضاء الكثير من الوقت في النظر إلى مختلف المجسّمات
and understanding where they come from.
وفي فهم مصدرهم.
It's a crazy Matrix experience.
إنها تجربة مجنونة ومعقّدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just moving on,
لنتابع إذاً،
let's take the world-famous Vincent Van Gogh,
لنأخذ مثلا الرسام المشهور عالميا فينسينت فان كوخ،
who is very well-represented on this platform.
الذي تمّ تمثيله بشكل رائع على هذه المنصّة.
Thanks to the diversity of the institutions we have,
بفضل تنوّع المؤسسات التي نعمل معها،
we have over 211 high-definition, amazing artworks by this artist,
لدينا أكثر من 211 عمل فنّي بجودة عالية لهذا الفنان،
now organized in one beautiful view.
وهي مرتبة الآن في مشهد جميل واحد.
And as it resolves, and as Cyril goes deeper,
التي تزداد وضوحاً كلما اقترب سيريل أكثر،
you can see all the self-portraits,
يمكنكم أن تشاهدوا جميع اللوحات الذاتية،
you can see still life.
تنبض بالحياة.
But I just wanted to highlight one very quick example,
ولكنّي أرغب بعجالة بتسليط الضوء علي المثال التالي،
which is very timely:
في الوقت المناسب:
"The Bedroom."
"غرفة النوم".
This is an artwork where three copies exist --
هذا عمل فني له ثلاث نسخ --
one at the Van Gogh Museum in Amsterdam,
واحدة في متحف فان كوخ في أمستردام،
one at the Orsay in Paris
واحدة في الأورسي في باريس
and one at the Art Institute of Chicago,
وواحدة في معهد الفن في شيكاغو،
which, actually, currently is hosting a reunion
والذي يشهد حاليًا حدث لمّ شمل
of all three artworks physically,
للنسخ الثلاث علي أرض الواقع،
I think only for the second time ever.
أعتقد أن هذا يحدث للمرة الثانية فقط .
But, it is united digitally and virtually for anybody to look at
ولكن هذه النسخ متوفرة معًا رقميًا وافتراضيًا لأي شخص يرغب بالإطلاع عليها
in a very different way,
بطريقة مختلفة تمامًا.
and you won't get pushed in the line in the crowd.
ولن تضطر للتدافع وأنت تقف ضمن الحشود.
So let's take you and let's travel through "The Bedroom" very quickly,
إذًا دعوني أصطحبكم لنسافرعبر لوحة "غرفة النوم" وبسرعة،
so you can experience what we are doing for every single object.
حيث يمكنكم أن تطلعوا على ما نقوم به لكل مجسّم على حدة.
We want the image to speak as much as it can
نريد للصورة أن تتكلّم قدر الإمكان
on a digital platform.
غلى منصّة رقمية.
And all you need is an internet connection and a computer
وكل ما تحتاجونه، هو اتصال باإنترنت وكمبيوتر
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And, Cyril, if you can go deeper, quickly.
سيريل، قرِّ أكثر، بسرعة.
I'm sorry, this is all live,
أعتذر، فكل هذا يحدث مباشرة،
so you have to give Cyril a little bit of --
لذا عليكم منح سيريل القليل من --
and this is available for every object:
وهذا متاح لجميع المجسّمات:
modern art, contemporary art, Renaissance -- you name it,
الفن الحديث والمعاصر وفن النهضة -- سمّوا ما شئتم،
even sculpture.
حتى النّحت.
Sometimes, you don't know what can attract you
أحيانًا لا تعلمون تمامًا ما الذي قد يجذبكم
to an artwork or to a museum or to a cultural discovery.
لعمل فنّي أو لمتحف ما أو لاكتشاف ثقافيّ ما.
So for me, personally, it was quite a challenge
لذلك بالنسبة لي شخصيّاً، كان هذا يمثّل تحدياً إلى حدّ ما
because when I decided to make this my full-time job at Google,
لأنّي عندما قررت أن أعمل بهذا بدوام كامل لدى غوغل،
my mother was not very supportive.
لم أحظ بدعم كبير من والدتي.
I love my mother,
أحبّ والدتي،
but she thought I was wasting my life with this museum stuff.
ولكنّها ظنّت أنني أهدر حياتي مع أمور المتاحف هذه.
And for her, a museum is what you do when you go on vacation
وبالنسبة لها، المتحف هو ما تقوم به أثناء الإجازة
and you tick-mark and it's over, right?
وتزوره مرة واحدة، وانتهى الأمر، أليس كذلك؟
And it took around four and a half years
واحتجت لحوالي أربع سنوات ونصف
for me to convince my lovely Indian mother
لإقناع والدتي الهندية الحبيبة بانّ
that actually, this is worthwhile.
ما أقوم به فعلاً يستحقّ العناء.
And the way I did it was, I realized one day that she loves gold.
وكانت طريقة إقناعها، أني لاحظت في أحد الأيام أنها تحبّ الذهب.
So I started showing her all objects that have the material gold in them.
لذلك جعلتها تشاهد كل المجسّمات التي تحتوي على مادة الذهب.
And the first thing my mom asks me is,
وأول أمر سألتني والدتي عنه،
"How can we buy these?"
"كيف يمكننا شراء هذه الأشياء؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And obviously, my salary is not that high,
ومن الواضح، أنّ راتبي ليس كبيراً بما يكفي،
so I was like, "We can't actually do that, mom.
لذلك كان ردّي " لايمكننا فعل ذلك، يا أمّي.
But you can explore them virtually."
"ولكنك تستطيعين استكشافهم افتراضيًا".
And so now my mom -- every time I meet her, she asks me,
الآن في كل مرّة أقابلها، تسألني،
"Any more gold, any more silver in your project? Can you show me?"
"هل يوجد المزيد من الذهب والفضة في مشروعك؟ هل تستطيع أن تريني إيّاها؟"
And that's the idea I'm trying to illustrate.
وهذه الفكرة التي أحاول شرحها.
It does not matter how you get in,
ليس المهم كيف تعرفت علي الأمر،
as long as you get in.
طالما أنه أعجبك.
Once you get in, you're hooked.
ما أن أثير اهتمامكم، فقد عَلِقتم.
Moving on from here very quickly,
لننتقل من هنا بسرعة،
there is kind of a playful idea, actually,
هناك فكرة مرحة هنا، في الحقيقة،
to illustrate the point of access,
لشرح أهمية الوصول،
and I'm going to go quite quickly on this one.
وسأمرّ بها بسرعة.
We all know that seeing the artwork in person is amazing.
كلنا نعلم أنّ مشاهدة عمل فنيّ شخصيّاً هو أمر استثنائي.
But we also know that most of us can't do it,
ولكن نعلم أيضًا أنّ معظمنا لا تتاح له الفرصة،
and the ones that can afford to do it, it's complicated.
حتي لأولئك القادرين، فالأمر معقّد.
So -- Cyril, can we load up our art trip, what do we call it?
سيريل، هل بالإمكان تحميل رحلتنا الفنية ماذا ندعوها؟
We don't have a good name for this.
ليس لدينا اسم مناسب لها.
But essentially, we have around 1,000 amazing institutions,
بشكل أساسيّ، لدينا حوالي 1000 مؤسسة استثنائية،
68 countries.
68 بلد.
But let's start with Rembrandt.
لكن لنبدأ ب "ريمبراندت".
We might have time for only one example.
ربما يسمح لنا الوقت بمثال واحد فقط.
But thanks to the diversity,
لكن بفضل التنوع،
we've got around 500 amazing Rembrandt object artworks
لدينا حوالي 500 مجسّم فنّي لريمبراندت
from 46 institutions and 17 countries.
من 46 مؤسسة من 17 بلداً.
Let's say that on your next vacation,
لنفترض أنّكم وخلال إجازتكم القادمة،
you want to go see every single one of them.
تودّون الذهاب لرؤية كلّ منها على حدة.
That is your itinerary,
وهذا هو مساركم،
you will probably travel 53,000 kilometers,
من الأرجح أنّكم ستسافرون 53,000 كيلومتر،
visit around, I think, 46 institutions,
لزيارة حوالي 46 مؤسسة،
and just FYI, you might release 10 tons of CO2 emissions.
ولمعلوماتكم، سوف تطلقون 10 أطنان من غاز ثاني أكسيد الكربون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But remember, it's art,
ولكن تذكّروا، إنّه الفنّ،
so you can justify it, perhaps, in some way.
لذلك ستجدون تبريراً لكلّ هذا بطريقة أو بأخرى.
Moving on swiftly from here,
ننتقل بسرعة من هنا.
is something a little bit more technical and more interesting.
إلى أمر تقنيّ ومثير للاهتمام أكثر.
All that we've shown you so far uses metadata to make the connections.
كلّ ما عرضناه عليكم إلى حدّ الآن، يستخدم بيانات التعريف لتأسيس الاتصال.
But obviously we have something cool nowadays
ولكن لدينا اليوم شيء لطيف
that everyone likes to talk about, which is machine learning.
يرغب الجميع بالحديث عنه، وهو "تعلّم الآلة".
So what we thought is, let's strip out all the metadata,
لذلك خطر لنا، لنتخلص من جميع بيانات التعريف،
let's look at what machine learning can do
ولنرى ما يستطيع "تعلّم الآلة "القيام به
based purely on visual recognition of this entire collection.
حيث تعتمد بشكل محض على الملاحظة البصرية لكامل المجموعة.
What we ended up with is this very interesting map,
وخلُصنا إلى هذه الخريطة المثيرة للاهتمام،
these clusters that have no reference point information,
هذه المجموعات التي ليس لديها أيّ معلومات مرجعية،
but has just used visuals to cluster things together.
ولكن بمجرد استخدام الوسائل البصرية أدّى إلى تجمع الأشياء معًا.
Each cluster is an art to us by itself of discovery.
كل مجموعة تمثل بالنسبة لنا فن يستحق الإستكشاف.
But one of the clusters we want to show you very quickly
ونريد أن نعرض أحدها عليكم بسرعة
is this amazing cluster of portraits
وهي مجموعة رائعة من اللوحات
that we found from museums around the world.
والتي حصلنا عليها من متاحف حول العالم.
If you could zoom in a little bit more, Cyril.
كبر الصورة قليلاً، سيريل.
Just to show you, you can just travel through portraits.
وذلك لنبرهن لكم أنه بإمكانكم التجوال عبر اللوحات.
And essentially, you can do nature, you can do horses
بشكل أساسي يمكنكم الإطلاع على الطبيعة، الخيول
and clusters galore.
ومجموعات أخري وفيرة.
When we saw all these portraits,
عندما نرى كل هذه اللوحات،
we were like, "Hey, can we do something fun for kids,
فكرنا: "هل يمكننا القيام بأمر ممتع للأطفال،
or can we do something playful
أو شيء مسلي
to get people interested in portraits?"
لجذب اهتمام النّاس في هذه اللوحات؟"
Because I haven't really seen
لأنني حتى الآن لم أرَ
young kids really excited to go to a portrait gallery.
أطفالاً صغار يتحمّسون للذهاب إلى معرض لوحات.
I wanted to try to figure something out.
أردت إيجاد حلّ ما.
So we created something called the portrait matcher.
لذلك أنشأنا ما يسمى مُطَابِق الصور.
It's quite self-explanatory,
وهذا يفسّرنفسه بسهولة.
so I'm just going to let Cyril show his beautiful face.
لذلك سأطلب من سيريل أن يرينا وجهه الجميل.
And essentially what's happening is, with the movement of his head,
وبشكل أساسيّ، ما يحدث أنه ومع حركة رأسه،
we are matching different portraits around the world from museums.
نُطابِق لوحات مختلفة من متاحف حول العالم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I don't know about you,
ولا أعلم ما الذي تظنونه،
but I've shown it to my nephew and sister,
لكنّي عرضت ذلك على أختي وابنها،
and the reaction is just phenomenal.
وكانت ردة فعلهم استثنائية.
All they ask me is, "When can we go see this?"
وسألوني فقط:"متى يمكننا مشاهدة هذا؟"
And by the way, if we're nice,
وبالمناسبة، لو أحسنا التصرّف،
maybe, Cyril, you can smile and find a happy one?
ربما، سيريل يمكنك الابتسام لتجد لنا واحدة سعيدة؟
Oh, perfect.
أوه، رائع.
By the way, this is not rehearsed.
بالمناسبة، لم نتمرن علي ذلك.
Congrats, Cyril. Great stuff. Oh wow.
أهنئك سيريل، صور رائعة.
OK, let's move on; otherwise, this will just take the whole time.
حسناً لنتابع، وإلّا سنحتاج وقتاً طويلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, art and culture can be fun also, right?
إذًا يمكن للفن والثقافة أن يكونوا ممتعين، أليس كذلك؟
For our last quick experiment --
من أجل تجربتنا الأخيرة --
we call all of these "experiments" --
ندعو كل هذا "تجارب" --
our last quick experiment comes back to machine learning.
تقودنا تجربتنا الأخيرة نعود إلي " تعليم الآلة."
We show you clusters, visual clusters,
عرضنا عليكم مجموعات ، مجموعات بصرية،
but what if we could ask the machine to also name these clusters?
لكن ماذا لوطلبنا من الآلة أن تسمّي هذه المجموعات؟
What if it could automatically tag them, using no actual metadata?
ماذا لو تمكنت من تأشيرهم تلقائيًا، وذلك دون استخدام أي بيانات تعريف فعلية؟
So what we have is this kind of explorer,
لذا ما حصلنا عليه هو نوع من المسكتشف،
where we have managed to match, I think, around 4,000 labels.
حيث نجحنا في مطابقة حوالي 4000 تسمية.
And we haven't really done anything special here,
ولم نقم بشيء خاص حقيقةً،
just fed the collection.
فقط قمنا بتزويد الآلة بالمجموعات.
And we found interesting categories.
ووجدنا فئات مثيرة للاهتمام.
We can start with horses, a very straightforward category.
يمكننا أن نبدأ بالخيول وهي فئة واضحة جدا.
You would expect to see that the machine has put
تتوقعون طبعاً أن الآلة ستضع
images of horses, right?
صوراً للخيول، أليس كذلك؟
And it has, but you also notice, right over there,
وهذا ما يحدث، ولكنكم تلاحظون أيضاً هناك تحديداً،
that it has a very abstract image
بأن لديها صورة أكثر تجريداً
that it has still managed to recognize and cluster as horses.
وما زالت قادرة على تحديدها وتجميعها في مجموعات الخيول.
We also have an amazing head in terms of a horse.
هنا يوجد رؤوس مذهلة فيما يخص الخيول.
And each one has the tags as to why it got categorized in this.
وكل منها لديه علامات توضّح لماذا صُنِفَت في هذه الفئة.
So let's move to another one which I found very funny and interesting,
لننتقل إلى أمر آخر أجده ممتع جداً ومثير للاهتمام.
because I don't understand how this category came up.
لأنّي لا أعلم كيف جاءت فكرة هذه الفئة.
It's called "Lady in Waiting."
التي تُسمى "سيدة مُنتَظِرة".
If, Cyril, you do it very quickly,
لو أمكنك سيريل أن تقوم بذلك بسرعة،
you will see that we have these amazing images
ستشاهدون أن لدينا هذه الصور المدهشة
of ladies, I guess, in waiting or posing.
لسيّدات، على ما أعتقد أنهم في حالة انتظار أو وضعية معينة.
I don't really understand it.
لا أفهمها تمامًا.
But I've been trying to ask my museum contacts,
أحاول الاستفسار من معارفي في المتحف،
you know, "What is this? What's going on here?"
"ما هذا؟ ما الذي يحدث هنا؟"
And it's fascinating.
إنه أمر مذهل.
Coming back to gold very quickly,
بالعودة إلى الذهب وبسرعة،
I wanted to search for gold
أردت البحث عن الذهب
and see how the machine tagged all the gold.
لأرى كيف تصنّف الآلة هذه الفئة.
But, actually, it doesn't tag it as gold.
فعليًا، لا تصنّفه الآله كـ"ذهب".
We are living in popular times.
نحن نعيش في عصور عصرية.
It tags it as "bling-bling."
تصنفه أنه "بلنغ-بلنغ" (مجوهرات ثمينة)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm being hard on Cyril, because I'm moving too fast.
أنا أجعل الأمر صعبًا على سيريل، لأنّي أنتقل بسرعة.
Essentially, here you have all the bling-bling
بشكل أساسي، لدينا هنا كل الـ "بلنغ-بلنغ"
of the world's museums organized for you.
الموجودة في متاحف العالم مرتّبة لكم.
And finally, to end this talk and these experiments,
وأخيراً، لنختم حديثنا وتجاربنا،
what I hope you feel after this talk is happiness and emotion.
أتمنى أن تشعروا بالسعادة والعاطفة بنهاية هذا الحديث.
And what would we see when we see happiness?
وماذا يمكننا أن نشاهد عندما نرى السعادة؟
If we actually look at all the objects
إذا ما بحثنا في كل المجسّمات
that have been tagged under "happiness,"
التي صنّفت تحت مسمّى "السّعادة"،
you would expect happiness, I guess.
تتوقعون أن تشاهدوا السعادة، على ما أعتقد.
But there was one that came up that was very fascinating and interesting,
تظهرإحدى الصور الرائعة جداً والمثيرة للاهتمام.
which was this artwork by Douglas Coupland,
وهي هذا العمل الفنّي لدوغلاس كوبلاند،
our friend and artist in residence as well,
صديق وفنّان لدينا أيضا،
called, "I Miss My Pre-Internet Brain."
تدعى"أشتاق لدماغي ماقبل الانترنت"
I don't know why the machine feels like it misses its pre-Internet brain
لا أعلم لماذا تفتقد الآلة دماغها ما قبل الانترنت
and it's been tagged here,
ووضعته في هذا التصنيف هنا،
but it's a very interesting thought.
ولكنه تفكير مثير للاهتمام.
I sometimes do miss my pre-Internet brain,
أحياناً أفتقد دماغي ما قبل الانترنت،
but not when it comes to exploring arts and culture online.
ولكن ليس عندما يتعلّق الأمر باكتشاف الفنّون والثقافة.
So take out your phones, take out your computers,
لذلك أخرجوا هواتفكم وحواسبكم،
go visit museums.
واذهبوا لزيارة المتاحف.
And just a quick call-out to all the amazing archivists,
فهي وسيلة سريعة للوصول إلى جميع المؤرشفين المذهلين،
historians, curators,
المؤرخين، أمناء المتاحف،
who are sitting in museums, preserving all this culture.
الموجودين في المتاحف للحفاظ على كل هذه الثقافة.
And the least we can do is get our daily dose of art and culture
وأقل ما يمكن أن نقوم به، أن تحصل علي جرعة يومية من الفنّ والثقافة
for ourselves and our kids.
لأجلنا ولأجل أبنائنا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)